<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: batch script | .NET, Sitecore and setup development]]></title>
  <link href="http://yansklyarenko.github.io/blog/categories/batch-script/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yansklyarenko.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-03-25T23:33:28+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://yansklyarenko.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Yan Sklyarenko]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A simple batch script to dump the contents of the folder and its subfolders recursively]]></title>
    <link href="http://yansklyarenko.github.io/blog/2012/03/02/simple-batch-script-to-dump-contents-of/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-02T11:13:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://yansklyarenko.github.io/blog/2012/03/02/simple-batch-script-to-dump-contents-of</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<div dir="ltr" style="text-align: left;" trbidi="on">This topic might seem too minor for a blog post. You can argue that it’s covered by a simple call to a <strong><a href="http://ss64.com/nt/dir.html">dir /s</a></strong> command. Well, that’s true unless you need to perform some actions with each line in the list. In this case it could be tricky if you do not use BATCH files on a daily basis. <br />Imagine you need to dump the file paths in a folder and its subfolders to a plain list. Besides, you’d like to replace the absolute path prefix with UNC share prefix, because each path contains a shared folder and each file will be accessible from inside the network. So, here goes the script:<br /><div class="wlWriterEditableSmartContent" id="scid:f32c3428-b7e9-4f15-a8ea-c502c7ff2e88:5c4445c5-847e-4642-8167-0397b2755daa" style="display: inline; float: none; margin: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px; padding-left: 0px; padding-right: 0px; padding-top: 0px;"><pre class="brush: vb;">@echo off<br />set _from=*repo<br />set _to=\\server\repo<br />FOR /F "tokens=*" %%G IN ('dir /s /b /a:-D /o:-D') DO (CALL :replace %%G) &gt;&gt; files.txt<br />GOTO :eof<br /><br />:replace<br /> set _str=%1<br /> call set _result=%%_str:%_from%=%_to%%%<br /> echo %_result%<br />GOTO :eof</pre></div><br />Let’s start from the <a href="http://ss64.com/nt/for_cmd.html">FOR</a> loop. This version of the command loops through the output of another command, in this case, dir. Essentially, we ask dir to run recursively (/s), ignore directories (/a:-D), sort by date/time, newest first (/o:-D) and output just the basic information (/b). And the FOR command works on top of this, iterating all lines of dir output (tokens=*), calling a subroutine :replace for each line and streaming the final result into files.txt.<br /><br />The subroutine does a very simple thing – it replaces one part of the string with another. Let’s step through it anyway. First, it gets the input parameter (%1) and saves it into _str variable. I suppose %1 could be used as is in the expression below, but the number of ‘%’ signs drives me crazy even without it. The next line is the most important – it does the <a href="http://ss64.com/nt/syntax-replace.html">actual replacement job</a>. I’ll try to explain all these % signs: the variable inside the expression must be wrapped with % (like _from and _to); the expression itself should go between % and % as if it’s a variable itself. And the outermost pair of % is there for escaping purpose, I suppose – you will avoid it if you use just string literals for tokens in expression. Note also the usage of the <a href="http://ss64.com/nt/call.html">CALL SET statement</a>. Finally, the last line of the subroutine echoes the result.<br /><br />There’s one last point worth attention. The _from variable, which represents the token to replace, contains a * sign. It means “replace ‘repo’ and everything before it” in the replace expression.<br /><br />The best resource I found on the topic is <a href="http://ss64.com/nt/">http://ss64.com/nt/</a>.</div></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
