<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: torch | .NET, Sitecore and setup development]]></title>
  <link href="http://yansklyarenko.github.io/blog/categories/torch/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yansklyarenko.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-03-25T23:33:28+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://yansklyarenko.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Yan Sklyarenko]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Torch.exe confuses the language validation and ProductCode validation]]></title>
    <link href="http://yansklyarenko.github.io/blog/2010/05/07/torchexe-confuses-langauge-validation/"/>
    <updated>2010-05-07T19:34:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://yansklyarenko.github.io/blog/2010/05/07/torchexe-confuses-langauge-validation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>This week I faced with another issue with torch.exe. As you might know, there’s a “type” option (-t) to apply a predefined set of validation flags to the generated transform. If you’d like to generate a language transform, you should use “-t language”. It should suppress all the errors plus validate that language in both MSI packages corresponds. But it doesn’t…</p>  <p>The reason is just a simple bug in the tool. When you set “-t language” in the command line, this option is mapped to the TransformFlags.LanguageTransformDefault value. It is a combination of atomic values (those you can set via –serr and -val), and it mistakenly takes “validate product code” bit instead of “validate language bit”. I’ve never noticed this unless my installation uses both instance transforms and language transforms.</p>  <p>The workaround is quite simple: use literally “–serr” and “–val” to achieve the same result. For instance, for language transform it should be:</p>  <p>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; torch.exe … –serr a –serr b –serr c –serr d –serr e –serr f –val l …</p>  <p>[By the way, does it look too long just for me? I would prefer –serr abcdef :-)]</p>  <p>I’ve also filed an <a href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/?func=detail&amp;aid=2998229&amp;group_id=105970&amp;atid=642714">issue</a> to the WiX toolset. Hope this can help somebody.</p>  </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Torch.exe throws scary error message unrelated to the real problem]]></title>
    <link href="http://yansklyarenko.github.io/blog/2010/04/14/torchexe-throws-scary-error-message/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-14T15:35:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://yansklyarenko.github.io/blog/2010/04/14/torchexe-throws-scary-error-message</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Today I’ve been working on the localization of my installation project, and I had to create a number of language transforms. The following simple call of torch.exe</p>  <p>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; torch -t language setup.msi setup_ru-ru.msi -out mst\ru-ru.mst</p>  <p>returned the scary error message:</p>  <p>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; error TRCH0001 : The Windows Installer service failed to start. Contact your support personnel</p>  <p>I’ve seen this kind of errors a couple of times, and it was a serious problem with Windows Installer engine on the target machine in all cases. Once, it indicated that Windows Installer service is completely broken, and only OS reinstall helped (fortunately, it was virtual PC)… But mighty Google gave <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/pmarcu/archive/2008/05/30/Patching-something-you-didnt-build-with-WiX-using-WiX-.aspx#8920333">a single, but exact hint</a>. It is just a single line, and one can miss the point since that’s another problem which is discussed there. </p>  <p>So, the actual problem: if –out switch points to a folder which doesn’t exist (‘mst’ in this case), torch.exe can’t create it and returns the error. That’s okay behavior to live with, but the error message should be changed to something more appropriate: “The folder ‘mst’ can’t be found. Make sure it exists before referencing in –out switch”. I’ve also created <a href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/?func=detail&amp;aid=2987095&amp;group_id=105970&amp;atid=642714">an issue</a> to the WiX inbox at sourceforge.net.</p>  <p>Hope this info is helpful until the message text is fixed.</p>  </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
